<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A True and joyfull relation of two famous battels fought against the Lord Marquesse of Hartford the first by the Earle of Pembroke and the Earle of Bedfords forces ... who having joyned their forces together, marched towards Sherborn-castle and assaulted it, where the marquesse had strongly intrenched himself, but after one day spent, obtained the victorie : together with the Earl of Pembrokes proceedings in the county of VViltshire ... : the second ar glorious victory obtained by the Parliaments forces against the cavaleers neer Norvvich and Poole ... / ordered by the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, that this be forthwith printed and published, John Brown, Cler. Parl.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2508A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43785</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475241</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475241</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151399</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94930)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151399)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2258:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A True and joyfull relation of two famous battels fought against the Lord Marquesse of Hartford the first by the Earle of Pembroke and the Earle of Bedfords forces ... who having joyned their forces together, marched towards Sherborn-castle and assaulted it, where the marquesse had strongly intrenched himself, but after one day spent, obtained the victorie : together with the Earl of Pembrokes proceedings in the county of VViltshire ... : the second ar glorious victory obtained by the Parliaments forces against the cavaleers neer Norvvich and Poole ... / ordered by the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament, that this be forthwith printed and published, John Brown, Cler. Parl.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Watkins,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>August 27, 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, cropped, and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Campaigns.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151399:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <p>A TRUE and JOYFULL RELATION Of two Famous</p>
            <p>Battels fought againſt the Lord Marqueſſe of <hi>Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> The firſt by the Earle of <hi>Pembroke</hi> and the Earle of <hi>Bedfords</hi> Forces, being in Number. 800 foot, and 4000, horſe, who having joyned their Forces together, marched towards <hi>Shereborn-caſtle</hi> and aſſaulted it, where the Marqueſſe had ſtrongly intrenched him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but after one day ſpent, obtained the Victorie.</p>
            <p>Together with the <hi>Earl of Pembrokes</hi> Proceedings in the County of VViltshite Read in the Houſe of Commons upon <hi>Friday, Auguſt</hi> 26. <hi>and immediatly Ordered to be printed, it being very joyfull and delectable Tydings to all true</hi> PROTESTANTS,</p>
            <p>The ſecond a Glorious Victory obtained by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Forces againſt the Cavaleeres neer <hi>Norvvich</hi> and <hi>Poole, with the Number of thoſe that were ſlain on both ſides, and the Parliaments command to all Lieutenants in every ſeverall county.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Ordered by the Lords and Commons aſsembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that this be forthwith printed and publiſhed.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>John. Brown. Cler. Parl.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>Printed for <hi>R. Watkins Auguſt</hi> 27. 1642.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151399:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:151399:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:151399:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:151399:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <head>A FAMOUS <hi>BATTELL</hi> FOVGHT BETWIXT THE TRAYNED Band of <hi>Poole</hi> in the county <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetſhire,</hi> and the Lord Marqueſſe of <hi>Hartford, Auguſt</hi> 25.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ong hath the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the <hi>Marqueſse of Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> ſtruck terrour in the county of <hi>Sommerſet,</hi> but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he could not prevail in thoſe parts, he then marched with ſpeed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:151399:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
               <hi>Dorcheſter and Poole,</hi> with a great Number of men, who comming there, he deſired and propounded theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Propoſition unto the Major and Citiſens of <hi>Poole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>That they would deliver and reſign up the Town unto him, and in ſo doing, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty would account them true, and Loyall Subiects, and eſteeme of them hereafter ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordiig to their Deſarts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>That as his Maieſty hath bin pleaſed to Grant unto him the Title and to make him Lord Lieutenant Generall of all Wales, Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetſhire, Sommerſetſhire, &amp;c. yet thought no place ſo fit to entertain his Greatneſſe as Pool, therfore hee deſired them to ſurrender up the town but they would not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherupon they immediatly fell to blowes, but after ſome two hours fight, the Marqueſſe had the worſt out, having loſt a great Number of men in the ſaid Skirmiſh.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151399:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <p>Upon <hi>Wedneſday</hi> laſt being, the 24 of this inſtant month of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was given by Letters from <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> that ſome of the Cavaleers belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Kings Army came to tge ſaid town upon Tueſday laſt putting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in battle array againſt it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they could aſſault it, the Parliament Forces marched againſt them, charging very couragiouſly againſt them alſo, and within the ſpace of two hours, there was ſlain of the Cavaleers about 30, wich very little loſſe on the other ſide.</p>
            <p>Wherupon the Houſe fell into conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of haſtning away more Forces to be ſent to aſſiſt thoſe that are gone already.</p>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>Pembroke</hi> is gone down into <hi>Wilsshire,</hi> and doth oppoſe all thoſe that ſtands againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the aſſiſtance of the whole county expreſſing their willingneſſe towards him, and hath alſo ſent him 800. Horſe with men well armed, ſo that the Earle doth not fear the whole Army of Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leers,</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151399:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
            <p>There was alſo upon this inſtant month of <hi>August,</hi> many skirmiſhes in <hi>Dorſetſhire, betwixt the Inhabitants thereof and the Marqueſse of Hartford, the Procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings whereof, are here in this enſuing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation made manifeſt, the Commons Houſe of Parliament having information of the ſame, as is plainly related in theſe enſuing Particulars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon the 22. of this inſtant month of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> information was given to the Houſe of the Reſolution of the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of Hartford</hi> to ceize upon the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazine</hi> at <hi>Dorcheſter</hi> and <hi>Poole,</hi> but the ſaid Town have bravely fortified them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and have mounted above 30. pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Ordnance</hi> againſt thhe ſaid <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſse,</hi> labouring and indeavouring dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make trenches to prevent the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of the Marqueſſe and his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and the ſaid Marqueſſe is in great Fear, that the Earl of <hi>Pembroke,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Bedford</hi> will come ſo ſtrong a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, that they ſhall not be able to reſiſt their Force, the ſaid Earls having
<pb facs="tcp:151399:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->in Number about 800. Horſe, and 4000 Foot, and as it is credibly reported are marched in a full Body towards <hi>Shere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Caſtle,</hi> being reſolved to lay ſiege a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſame.</p>
            <p>But it is thought that the Marqueſſe is extraordinary ſtrong, and hath ſet down his Reſolution to reſiſt and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his life againſt all thoſe that ſhall offer or preſume ſo farre to oppoſe him having command from his Majeſty to raiſe all Forces that he poſſible can, for the ſafety of the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Yet the Earls of <hi>Pembroke</hi> and <hi>Bedford</hi> having joyned their Forces, marched to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the ſaid Caſtle of <hi>Shereborn,</hi> and aſſaulted it, inſomuch that there inſued a great and bloudy battell betwixt the Marqueſſe and the Earles Forces, where having ſpent the greateſt part of the day in hot ſervice one againſt the other, the Marqueſſe ſounded a parley, where ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome conſultation therupon, the fight was referred rill another day, and it is thought that about the 29. of this
<pb facs="tcp:151399:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->month they have â generall meeting, where they are reſolved to fight a pitcht Battle.</p>
            <p>And although his Majeſty at the raiſing of his Army from before Coventry gave them 3. dayes Reſpit for the Rendring it up; yet it is thought the Cavaleers will ſcarce come againe to demand it, for as yet it is not certainly known which way they are gone, many of them being lately fled from Warwick, and it is Reported by ſome that come out of thoſe parts, that the Earle of Northampton will fly away before the Parliament Forces come thither, although they are not above ſixe miles from Warwick.</p>
            <p>It is declared by the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons aſſembled in <hi>Parliament,</hi> that all <hi>Lieutenants, Deputy-Lieutenants,</hi> and other His Majeſties Officers, and loving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, ſhall aid and aſſiſt his Excellence the <hi>Earl of Eſſex,</hi> as need ſhall require, in defence of His Majeſties Subjects from all oppreſſion and violence with the power of the Counties and Trained Bands.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <p>Ordered by the Lords and Commons aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Parlament, that this be forthwith printed and publiſhed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Brown Cler. Parl.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:151399:6"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
